A Guide to the Confederate Prison Muster Roll, Castle Thunder, Richmond, Virginia, 1864
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Confederate Prison Muster Roll, Castle Thunder, Richmond, Virginia 1864
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11362
The collection consists of a single manuscript.
This 1864 manuscript document, "Morning Report of Capt. L. W. Richardson, Assistant Provost Marshal, Eastern District Military Station, A. P. Marshal's Office, Richmond, Va., April 27, 1864" lists fifty-eight prisoners, both Union and Confederate soldiers (all privates) and civilians, men and women, blacks and whites, confined or released from Castle Thunder Prison, Richmond. It provides details including date of incarceration, regiment and state, cause of arrest, and other details. L. W. Richardson signed it as "Capt. & APM [Assistant Provost Marshal], Comd [Commanding?]," and countersigned by "Officer of the Guard Lt. W. G. B. Andrews, Co. C, 10 VA. Battery Hy. Artillery" [2nd Lieutenant William B. G. Andrews, Company C, 10th Battalion Virginia Heavy Artillery]. The verso file docket bears the notation "Report Castle Thunder April 27 1864."
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Library purchased this document from Alexander Autographs, Inc., Cos Cob, Connecticut, January 7, 1998. It bears no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Lucien W. Richardson enlisted at Williamsburg in May 1861 as a member of the 1st Virginia Artillery, Company B, James City Artillery, eventually reaching the rank of captain. (In some records Richardson's first name is spelled "Lucian.") He remained with this unit when it became the 1st Battalion Virginia Light Artillery, Co. B, James City Artillery and later an independent unit, Captain Lucien W. Richardson's Battery of Virginia Artillery. Detailed to enrolling duty in January 1863, Richardson's poor health led to his reassignment to duty in Richmond by order of the Confederate Secretary of War. By December 1863 Richardson was a staff officer for General John H. Winder (1800-1865), provost marshal of Richmond.
Two June 1864 inspection reports describe Richardson as commandant of Castle Thunder (a Richmond prison part of the Eastern District Military Prison system and used to house Union and political prisoners) in charge of three lieutenants and commended for his "most excellent system of records and registry... office books are neatly and accurately kept, and exhibit a complete and comprehensive record of each prisoner received." One inspection reported noted "Captain R. is applying to be retired." [Jeffrey C. Weaver, Brunswick Rebel, Johnston, Southside, United, James City, Lunenburg Rebel, Pamunkey Heavy Artillery, and Young's Harborguard(Lynchburg, Virginia: H. E. Howard, Inc., 1996), 121; Joseph H. Crute, Confederate Staff Officers, 1861-1865(Powhatan, Va.: Derwent Books, 1982), 213; Lee A. Wallace, A Guide to Virginia Military Organizations, 1861-1865, rev. 2nd ed. (Lynchburg, Virginia: H. E. Howard, Inc., 1986), 2, 3-4, 31, 308; U. S. War Department, The War of the Rebellion: A Compilation of the Official Records of The Union and Confederate Armies(Washington: Government Printing Office, 1880-1901), series 2, vol.7, 204, 206, inspection reports.]
William B. G. Andrews enlisted as a private with the 10th Battalion Virginia Heavy Artillery [also know as "Allen's Battalion Virginia Heavy Artillery"], Company C [Allen Artillery] in Patrick County in February 1862 and was eventually promoted from corporal (1862) to sergeant (March 1863) to second lieutenant (October 1863). Ironically, in April 1865, he was captured by Union forces in Richmond, became a prisoner of war and hospitalized at a the Point of Rocks hospital suffering from diarrhea. Shortly after his transfer to Newport News, Andrews died in June 1865 of chronic diarrhea. [Jeffrey C. Weaver, 10th and 19th Battalions of Heavy Artillery (Lynchburg, Virginia: H. E. Howard, Inc., 1996), 6, 69.]
Scope and Content Information
This 1864 manuscript document, "Morning Report of Capt. L. W. Richardson, Assistant Provost Marshal, Eastern District Military Station, A. P. Marshal's Office, Richmond, Va., April 27, 1864" lists fifty-eight prisoners, both Union and Confederate soldiers (all privates) and civilians, men and women, blacks and whites, confined or released from Castle Thunder Prison, Richmond. It provides details including date of incarceration, regiment and state, cause of arrest, and other details. L. W. Richardson signed it as "Capt. & APM [Assistant Provost Marshal], Comd [Commanding?]," and countersigned by "Officer of the Guard Lt. W. G. B. Andrews, Co. C, 10 VA. Battery Hy. Artillery" [2nd Lieutenant William B. G. Andrews, Company C, 10th Battalion Virginia Heavy Artillery]. The verso file docket bears the notation "Report Castle Thunder April 27 1864."
A variety of charges are listed including desertion, espionage, attempted escape, and aiding the enemy ("Yankees"). Column headings include: "Committed/ Names/ Rank/ Company/ State/ Cause of Arrest/ By Whom Arrested/ Date of Arrest/ Place of Arrest/ By Whom Committed/ Papers With/ Sent to Hospital/ Returned from Hospital/ By Whom Discharged/ No. Of Order/ To Whom Delivered/ Date of Release/ Remarks." The lower "half" of the document lists several prisoners apparently released ("Discharges") on 27 April 1864; most had been taken into custody between November 1863 and April 1864. Twenty of these prisoners, mostly Union deserters, were either sent to Libby Prison where they were apparently freed: "Sent to Libby Prison on Special Order No. 101, discharged by General Winder." (John Henry Winder [1800- 1865] was provost marshal for Richmond and in charge of Union prisoners of war since 1861.)
Identified Confederate regiments include the 59th Alabama Infantry, 60th Alabama Infantry, 3rd Arkansas, 60th Georgia Infantry, 13th North Carolina Infantry, 29th North Carolina Infantry, 1st Virginia Infantry, 10th Battalion Virginia Heavy Artillery, 18th Virginia Cavalry, 41st Virginia Cavalry, 41st Virginia Infantry, 42nd Virginia Cavalry, 49th Virginia Infantry, 62nd Virginia Infantry, Carpenter's Company of Virginia Light Artillery, and, the Courtney Artillery (Virginia). Union infantry regiments include the 11th Connecticut, the 4th Delaware, the 16th Maine, the 9th, 23rd and 28th Massachusetts, the 2nd New Hampshire, the 12th New Jersey, the 11th, 44th, 52nd, 76th and 155th New York, the 2nd North Carolina, the 83rd and 97th Pennsylvania, the 12th U. S. Regulars, and the 1st Wisconsin. Arrested civilians include Charles [Emmerson?], Francis Fitzhugh (a "Free [Black] Woman"), J. Garletts, Mrs. S. E. Garletts, and a Dr. Macon.
Contents List
- Henry Crump, private, Co. B, 52nd New York 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  paroled Federal deserter, escaped from Coal Pitts, Chatham County, North Carolina, committed by Capt. Richardson
- Nicholas Gunger, private, Co. C, 76th New York 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  paroled Federal deserter, escaped from Chatham County, North Carolina, committed by Capt. Richardson
- [Silas] Murrah, private, Co. C, 59th Alabama Infantry 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  sentence of Court Martial, committed by Major Carrington
- George W. Harris, private, Co. H, 60th Alabama Infantry 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- [James] Shumaker, private, Co. H, 18th Virginia Cavalry 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  to be held for examination, committed by Major Carrington
- [James] Riley, private, Co. H, 41st Virginia Battalion [41st Virginia Cavalry] 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- [John] Lartairo [?], private, Co. H, 41st Virginia Battalion [41st Virginia Cavalry], to be held for examination, committed by Major Carrington 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  to be held for examinatyion, committed by Major Carrington
- J. Houdershell [John Howdishell], private, Co. A, 62nd Virginia [62nd Mounted Infantry] 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- [James S.] Price, private, Co. A, 62nd Virginia [62nd Mounted Infantry] 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- [Philip W.] Link, private, Co. A, 18th Virginia Cavalry 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- [James] Files, private, Co. K, 18th Virginia Cavalry 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- Dr. Macon, private [?] 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  committed as spy, committed by Major Carrington
- Benjamin Rudel, private, 1st Virginia Regiment 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  desertion, committed by Major Carrington, sent by General [John Cabell] Breckinridge
- John Ryan, private, Co. G, 42nd Virginia Cavalry 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  charges preferred, sent by Col. Robbins, committed by Capt Richardson, subject to order of Judge [James D.] Halyburton [Confederate District Court for Richmond]
- R.G. Allen, private, conscript 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  deserter from camp and attempting to get to the enemy, committed by Major Carrington, arrested by Col. Elliot
- M. Merrick, private, conscript 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- N. Green, private, conscript 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- R.B. Lehman, private, conscript 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- J. Garlettes, citizen 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  piloting deserters to Yankee lines, committed by Major Carrington, arrested by Col. Elliot
- Mrs. S.E. Garletts, citizen 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  until further orders, committed by Major Carrington, arrested by Col. Elliot
- W. Whitmore, private, Co. E, 11th Connecticut 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  Federal deserter, committed by Major Carrington
- Charles Fitzsimmons, private, Co. E, 11th Connecticut 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- Lewis Carter, private, Courtney Artillery [Virginia] 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  under sentence [Court] Martial, committed by Capt. Richardson, sent by Major Boyle
- Jessie F. Shepperson, private, James Battery [Courtney Artillery, Virginia] 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- George [R.] Kirkpatrick, private, Carpenter's Battery [Carpenter's Company of Virginia Light Artillery] 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- Thomas Rainey, private, Co. F, 28th Massachusetts 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  Federal deserter, committed by Capt. Richardson, sent by Major [Bindyford?]
- W. Jager, private, Co. F, 28th Massachusetts 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- [Ethadra W.] Lassiter, private, Co. F, 13th North Carolina [Infantry] 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  under sentence of Court Martial, committed by Capt. Richardson, sent by Major [Bindyford?]
- A. Reno [Alexander Renoe], private, Co. A, 49th Virginia [Infantry] 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
- Francis Fitzhugh, free woman [a free black; an "x" follows this] 1864 April 27 (Box 1)
  dischardb by General [John Henry] Winder, Special Order No. 101, delivered to M.W. [Jory?], released April 27 [1864]
- W.H. Green, private, Co. A, 3rd Arkansas [Cavalry] 1864 April 25 (Box 1)
  committed by Capt. Richardson, discharged by General [John Henry] Winder, Special order No. 101, delivered to Major Carrington, released April 27 [1864]
- J.C. Chumney, private, Co. A, 60th Georgia [Infantry] 1864 March 18 (Box 1)
  committed by Capt. Richardson, discharged by Capt. Vowles, Special Order No. 231, delivered to State Hospital, released April 27 [1864]
- J.A. Owens, private, Co. G, 60th Georgia [Infanty] 1864 March 18 (Box 1)
- Edward S. Scraggins, private, Co. C, 41st Virginia [Infantry] 1864 February 7 (Box 1)
  discharged by General Winder, Special Order No. 101, delivered to Lt. [Balis?], released April 27 [1864]
- Robert T. Newton, private, Co. C, 41st Virginia [Infantry] 1864 February 7 (Box 1)
  committed by Capt. Richardson, discharged by General Winder, Special Order No. 101, delivered to Lt. [Balis?], released April 27 [1864]
- Henry Putnam, private, 12th New Jersey Regulars [12th New Jersey] 1864 April 14 (Box 1)
  committed by Major Carrington, released April 27 [1864]
- Charles [Emmerson?], teamster 1864 April 14 (Box 1)
  committed by Major Carrington, "Sent to Libby Prison on Special Order No. 101, discharged by General Winder," released April 27 [1864]
- John Donnelly, private, Co. H, 97th Pennsylvania [Infantry] 1864 April 12 (Box 1)
  committed by Capt. Richardson, "Sent to Libby Prison on Special Order No. 101, discharged by General Winder," released April 27 [1864]
- George Slade, private, Co. D, 16th Maine [Infantry?] 1864 April 12 (Box 1)
- Joseph Boys, private, Co. C, 4th Delaware [Infantry?] 1864 April 11 (Box 1)
- Joseph Patton, private, Co. H, 11th Connecticut [Infantry?] 1864 April 10 (Box 1)
- [James] Howard, private, Co. I, 83rd Pennsylvania [Infantry] 1864 March 13 (Box 1)
  committed by Major Carrington, "discharged by General Winder, Sent to Libby Prison on Special Order No. 101," released April 27 [1864]
- L.H. Barrett, private, Co. D, 2nd North Carolina Infantry [a Union regiment] 1864 April 14 (Box 1)
- George Flynn, private, Co. I, 2nd New Hampshire [Infantry?] 1864 March 27 (Box 1)
  committed by Major Carrington, "discharged by General Winder, Sent to Libby Prison on Special Order No. 101, discharged by General Winder," released April 27 [1864]
- Thomas Brady, private, Co. K, 11th Connecticut 1864 April 8 (Box 1)
- [John W.] Fox, private, Co. K, 11th Connecticut Infantry 1864 April 8 (Box 1)
- [William] Howard, private, Co. K, 11th Connecticut Infantry 1864 April 8 (Box 1)
- A. Mullen, private, Co. A, 1st Wisconsin [Infantry?] 1864 March 28 (Box 1)
- [Patrick] Jones, private, Co. D, 44th New York [Infantry?] [1863] Nov 22 (Box 1)
  committed by Capt. Alexander, "Sent to Libby Prison on Special Order No. 101, discharged by General Winder," released April 27 [1864]
- A. Dickson, private, Y[ankee] Deserter 1864 February 11 (Box 1)
  committed by Major Griswold, "Sent to Libby Prison on Special Order No. 101, discharged by General Winder," released April 27 [1864]
- John Lawrence, private, Co. E, 23rd Massachusetts 1864 February 11 (Box 1)
  "Sent to Libby Prison on Special Order No. 101, discharged by General Winder," released April 27 [1864]
- [Theodore] German, private, Y[ankee] Deserter [1863] Dec 28 (Box 1)
- Robert Smith, private, Co. I, 2nd New Hampshire 1864 March 27 (Box 1)
- Charles Smith, private, Co. B, 11th New York 1864 April 1 (Box 1)
- John Randolph, private, Co. G, 155th New York 1864 April 1[?] (Box 1)
- [Thomas J.] Conner, private, Co. E, 9th Massachusetts Infantry 1864 April 1[?] (Box 1)
- A. Prater, private, Co. D, 2nd North Carolina Infantry [a Union regiment] 1864 April 4[?] (Box 1)
  Special Order No. 101, delivered to Lt. Bates, released April 27 [1864], to enlist in 29th North Carolina [Infantry] [Confederate]